hello and welcome everyone this is
active inference guest stream 28.1 it's
October 14 2022.
today we are going to be hearing and
discussing reconceiving rationality by
Giovanni Rolla so Giovanni thank you so
much for joining very much looking
forward to this presentation and
discussion so off to you thank you
thank you then it was a pleasure to to
receive your invitation a couple of
months ago and I am delighted to be here
to have this opportunity to discuss my
work
um I'll spare your request
um our suggestion I am uh presenting
this paper I wrote a couple of years ago
and uh as we were talking the backstage
I have I I've changed my mind a few
times and I'm going to make this clear
during the presentation since I
published that paper but it is a
pleasure nonetheless to have the chance
to present this video here and uh to to
share it with the world so I'm very
happy
uh so we'll be talking about
reconceiving rationality and this is the
this is the the
itinerary I was thinking about
presenting to you so first I'll be
talking about rationality and
contentless cognition then I'll present
my view which I called radically
inactive rationality and safety words
about agency and proficient interaction
and reasoning and rationality they are
close with a couple of objections the
first one being that whatever I'm
pressing here is uh too liberal in a way
excessively liberal it encompasses too
much and the second objection which I
think is the one that may interest to
you the most is whether it is in fact
compatible with predictive processing or
predictive coding which is of course in
the facility in the end it's near the
the tour of cars in central to do to
active Infinity so
here's the
here's the sorry
the my initial thoughts on the matter is
that traditionally the very
uh Orthodox have view on rationality
uh assumes to most of my knowledge it's
as an assumption really that rationality
must entail reason
that for instance I believe B in an
action a are rational if and only if
there is the reasoning that underwrites
in the Bure so and of course it's just
not any reasoning the reasoning question
must acquired with certain certain
formal benchmarks such as classical
logic or probability reasoning or
heuristics so believing and acting
rationally according to this traditional
field
require meeting certain formal standards
and this as I said it seems to me to be
largely an assumption about what it
means to be rational about defining
rationality in terms of reasoning
so if rationality requires reasoning
and if reasoning involves the evaluation
of beliefs against certain formal
benchmarks then rationality implies
content for cognition
where content I take it to be minimally
having accuracy conditions being capable
of being right or wrong or in or in on a
more
weightier notion being true or false so
the idea here is that rationality
necessarily involves content it involves
beliefs reasoning and the comparison or
sorry
to update right now
one software update I'm sorry there was
a a pop-up in my window over here so
um
that would be I think the the standard
view on rationality
and
if it is so that rationality necessarily
involves content it it is a good fit
with classical cognitivism or
cognitivism in general
which is the view that combination
necessarily involves representational
content at the very least for some
cognitivists of course it might involve
also
um
conceptual content but at the very least
representational content which has uh
accuracy conditions
but this classical view is not so good
it does not provide a so good fit with
radically inactive and embodied
cognition which I am here uh thinking
not specifically on radical and activism
by Goodwin Maine in the recent books but
I think it also challenges other views
that are not presented as radically and
active but of course they share some
core tenants with radical and activism
we could call them uh radically embodied
views of cognitions such as
um with the views presented by Ezekiel
Paulo
sensory model life you also have
Gallagher's enact variety variety of
inactivism in his 2017 book and also the
I mean the view by by Tony kimero in his
2009 book on ecological psychology and
dynamical systems they all share common
tenancy and here I am I know this is
very controversial but I'm treating
those views as radically embodied views
of cognition and but I'm specifically
focused on radical and active views of
cooking issue they all say that uh not
the recognition is representational
contentful which is in a way to say that
we can think of basic contentless forms
of cognition
or a contentless level basic level of
recognition
which emerges through the active
exploration of one's environment and
Beyond radical and activism by what we
mean
this could be this idea could be cashed
out in terms of mastering sensory motor
engagements a matter of know-how
the knowing how to engage with your
surroundings instead of knowing that
stuff are so and so around you so this
is very clearly what the Paulo and
colleagues and uh kimero for instance do
in their books uh radical and activism
has a certain tendency to skew sensory
model engagement sensory model schemes
Etc
and uh
but recent developments have I think
Incorporated that so the the this is the
use of the the list of this idea right
so if we combine radical embodied views
of Illumination or right connectivism
and the classical fuel on rationality
what we have is something that angle has
described as follows
and activism is the view that cognition
is grounded in a prayer rational
understanding of the world that is based
on sensory motor acquisition of real
life situation
and he explains these uh this idea of
pre-rational understanding
by
um
by by the the ideas of melopentin
Heidegger according to whom the relation
to the world can be only one written in
practice inactives in acting and
practicing intern is mediated through
the body so what seems to be implicit
here is that unlike acting and practice
rationality is not actually
it is something that is not at a very
basic level of combination so this is
what happened when we we
make room for a basic level of cognition
rooted in active and in practice and
divorce it from upper levels of
combination that they are usually the
locus the lucky Clarity of rationality
so
the idea in summation is that
contentious cognition or basic cognition
that which emerges through sensory motor
engagements is not rational
so sensory modern engagements however
virtues in prolific they can be cannot
be evaluated from the standpoint of
rationality only content for cognition
high level combination can be
rationality is expressed for instance in
beliefs and reasoning
and well this is something that I
haven't touched upon on the paper but it
was my implicit motivation to deal with
this subject
as someone that comes from philosophy of
the mind is the idea of the myth of the
given at least a version of it
it seemed to me at the time and uh I was
correctly persuaded by a reviewer not to
touch on the subject it was very
convoluted in my initial presentation
but it seems to me that if we divide
base recognition from a rational thought
and action and we do not Point towards
the
well there is no I mean intersection
between these two levels it seems that
radical and activism and uh similar
views would be committed to the myth of
the given unpopularized by Sellers and
moderations by McDowell as a problem for
imperious fields of my mind
so it seems that this is I think a
[Music]
a philosophically interesting problem
but it's not something that is uh on the
Forefront of the paper it was my
implicit motivation here that to explain
how can we combine the contentless or
basic level of cognition through sensory
modern engagements with rationality if
you cannot it seems that uh there is a
given of some sort that is being uh not
completely explained in our picture of
the mind so this is something I wanted
to I still want to try to explore this
this intuition more clearly but I
haven't
touched upon this
but I I think there's something in the
direction of what why what I will show
today is I think it's a way to tweeze
this this accusation of being committed
to the myth of the given
so how can we reconceive rationality I
mean I think in order to avoid that
issue and avoid the idea that we have
two levels completely separated from
each other where one The Higher One is
the locus classical rationality and what
else is beneath it is not rational I
think the idea is to rejected
rationality must be defined or it
entails necessarily reasoning
and nationality does not need to be
still conceived but then the challenge
becomes to offer a positive
proposal of what rationality is if not
reasoning and here is Susan Hurley in a
paper that my knowledge is the only one
that it's
upon this subject and I think she was
also concerned about the myth of the
given by the way at the time and he is a
long quote from her phenomide me reading
it is that rationality might emerge from
a complex system of the centralized
hierarchy relations of inhibition
facilitation and coordination among
different horizontal layers Each of
which is dynamic and environmentally
situated rationality reconceived in
horizontal or modular terms uh I don't
know if she has to use this this
terminology but in any way that's how
she chose to express it is substantively
related to the environment it does not
depend only on internal procedures that
mediate between input and output such as
content either for the organism as a
whole or for a vertically bounded
Central cognitive module rather it
depends on complex relationships between
dedicated World involving layers that
monitor and respond to specific aspects
of the natural and social environment
and of the neural network enriches the
feedback from their responses this to my
knowledge is the earliest case of
someone working on the inactive approach
in a way
is obviously more
usually associated with the work of
avano which is also an activist but
in a different approach from radical and
activism and here is the the earliest
and to my knowledge before I wrote that
paper is that the clearest
uh proposal of rationality reconceived
in the native terms but it's not it's
not something that uh gained traction
after her publication to my knowledge
actually I haven't seen much since then
and to summarize the idea is that we
have to change the explanatory Focus
which is rationality is not exclusively
thought of as a Content involving
capacity in this proposal it is situated
or World involved in increased words and
is it is radically embodied it depends
on bodily morphology and action
and how the the organism is situated and
acts in that environment the idea will
be minimally dead so this is what I call
radically inactive rationality
is uh in a very
uh lose definition so far is that an
Asian acts rationally in so far as she
maintains a proficient interaction with
her environment coordinating her green
capabilities according to environmental
conditions of constraints and solid
stations and of course this sometimes
requires adapting to unforeseen
circumstances the the the core intuition
is this
and it's interesting to compare this
idea of radical and active rationality
with another of Susan Hurley's ideas in
a text from 2003 she's she says
reasons uh for acting she argues that
reasons for acting maybe context bound
where she's having against uh Gareth
Evans generality constraint
and this is the defense of the idea of
islands of practical rationality
so she is still treating rationality as
essentially something that relates to
reasoning here but this kind of
reasoning is uh bounded by practical
context so this is a very Progressive
view if compared with the traditional
view I I talked about at the beginning
but still more conservative than what I
am trying to develop here
so another thing that I think must be uh
the Forefront of this proposal is that
rationality implies agency and autonomy
because something or only something that
an organism does can be said to be
rational right
so to use these uh the ideas from the
autonomous and activists camp and from
the theory of how to players is
autonomous systems such as a Roomba
cannot be rational because it's not an
agent it is not the author of its own
behavior it is designed by external
agents to work in a certain way so it's
not strictly speaking Nation so that is
where I would draw the line of where
well you cannot it makes no sense to
ascribe rationality to a Roomba for
instance
and
for this I I use the the Notions of
autonomy and adaptivity the DiPaolo and
others you have also the the recent book
image the four sensory model life and
that famous paper from the bowl from
2005 where he talks about the adaptivity
to to set his very general constraints
on what it means to be Russian
so autonomous systems are thereby
conceived as precarious networks a
precarious network of processes whose
organization and physical boundaries are
produced by the system itself the system
is continually maintaining its own uh
viability conditions which is
uh known as sense making where the
system explored uh environmental
environmental conditions that are
favorable to its uh self-maintenance and
avoids the ones that are detrimental to
it
so this is how I understand to be the
the very in general that the
emotional constraint on a rational being
that it must be an autonomous system
and the interesting thing here is that
the concept of adaptivity that Paulo
puts forth is that the capacity of an
organism to improve its condition of
self-production through internal
structural changes
so it involves the monitoring and
regulation of internal changes in order
to select the best available course of
action it is I think it's another
interesting concept to think in of to to
include in this idea of a radical and
active notion of rationality one that is
not necessarily committed to reasoning
and content
so agency is realized through the
exercise of situated abilities that
promote changes within the organism in
accordance with environmental
constraints and solid stations
which means that how well an organism
adapts in order to deal proficiently
with its environment is a measure of or
an indication of its rationality the
more rational an organism is the more
suited it is to deal with its
environment and we have foreseen
circumstances
and in doing so the organism enhances
The Continuous exchanges between itself
and the environment
which is crucial for its survival and it
is very
naturalized way of thinking of
rationality is mostly capacity to to
enhance changes for survival
this is the
the overall idea here
so as I said before what about reasoning
I want to
I don't want to commit rationality
necessarily with reasoning and this is
what radically inactive rationality is
all about but I don't want to exclude
reasoning as a former professional
combination
so what I'm saying is that it's not
defined by reasoning but it's not uh it
does not exclude reasoning reasoning I
think would be thought of as is special
or specific mode of rational agency one
that is exclusive to our knowledge to
human beings
but it's not the defining feature of
rationality
so for this I uh in order to to explain
this idea I recall how Hutu and Saturn
in between their people in a most recent
book by what I mean they explain the
emergence of high recognition the idea
is that being able to engage in content
for cognition ultimately depends on
being social culturally embedded
where content full cognition emerge from
social cultural interaction so as an
individual takes part in Social cultural
practices
they accept more ancient cognitive
abilities to deal with symbols and by
doing so they
um in a long process of enculturation of
course they become able to engage with a
symbolic coordination which is not
internal representation specific because
it is publicly available it's not mental
representations in the traditional sense
but it has the features of symbolic
cognition without the commitment to
there are no representation or mental
representations
so acting rationally in its most General
sense is the idea that the proficient
behavior of an organism is in is the
proficient behavior of an organism in
its environment it depends on the
coordination of embodied abilities
whereas reasoning if everything goes
well of course is understood as content
for rationality for my specific mode of
rationality reasoning is the proficient
behavior of an organism in a social
cultural environment
which is a more specific aspect of our
environment of course and it depends on
the coordination of such a culturally
based or content involving abilities
which are more recent in the the human
phylogenetic scale
so well this is the the biggest of the
idea this is the the I think uh the the
positive part and here are the
objections I wanted to talk about first
one being that it's a very liberal view
it's very
uh it it is well it decompasses too much
one would say because if rational action
boils down to the coordination of
cognitive abilities then rationality is
something gradual for an organism could
be more or less proficient in its
environmental interactions
and the the rejection goes according to
radically inactive rationality many
organisms achieve and maintain an
Adaptive behavior in the niche with
different levels of success
to which I am uh well someone could sing
rational and active radical and active
rationality is to Liberal and this is
one objection that I've heard in person
and I I kept it so hard because I think
it's very it's a very good way of
putting it even snails are rational on
this View and uh to which I must say
that I'm willing to to buy the bullet uh
well yes it's more liberal than
traditional views of course it is
intended to be so but I don't think that
this per se problem what I think is the
the positive part here is that it
preserves a difference of degree
humans are way more rational than other
animals simply because we are able to
perform a wide variety of actions in a
wide variety of dynamic circumstances
that are Way Beyond any other animals
that we are aware of
so to come back to the example of this
nail this nail can perform a few complex
actions can move from one point to
another it can search for food and
shelter and so on so forth but they have
a critical limited set of abilities if
you surround this nail with South for
instance it is doomed to to die by the
retortation and humans on the other hand
they are much more adaptive and able to
deal dynamically with many unforeseen
circumstances so uh
in my response that the rejection is
that yes
uh well it is very liberal but that's
not the problem the problem would be if
that it is if it had the room for a
difference of degree between how animals
deal with their environments
so and and this is the other object
objection which I think it may be though
the one that interests you the most then
you know is the 12 predictive processing
seems to imply inferences and content
all the way
uh but at first I must uh warn you and
the viewers that
at the time I wrote this uh this paper
was much more optimistic about this
possibility of combining an activism and
predictive coding or predictive
processing and uh I think there are
important points here but there is this
recent paper by Olu and Evan Thompson
and Randy beer where they uh they
provide a critical assessment of uh the
the the the attempts to combine mainly
the free energy principle and
um
inactive and
autobiographic theories so I am now
mostly convinced by their arguments but
I think there are some interesting
points of comparison here nonetheless
so predictive process in our predictive
code in uh at the time I was writing in
still to this day is all the raged in
the cognitive Sciences I guess you can
say that it sounded sweets become the
one of the main paradigms out there so
it is interesting to see if it provides
a good fit with what I'm talking about
and in these viewers you know
competition is understood as a process
of error minimization that occurs in
bidirectional narrow hierarchies
so
you have the generation of internal
models for the activity of lower layers
that anticipates the distal causes of
sinisterial stimuli which is a top-down
process and the minimization of
discrepancy between prediction and
current stimulus signal by
um the operation of priors which is a
bottom-up process
so here's of course active inference
which is understood by for instance in
an informal you know formal terms by
Clark an organism moves its sensors in
ways that amount to actively seek in our
generation generating the sensory
consequences that they are rather their
brains expect
this is one way of understanding active
influencing very among formal terms but
I think it gets the job done
so is the brain infaring the expected
source of received stimuli if it is
it seems that there is a there's an
issue with what I'm talking about
so the Hamilton reading of predictive
processing which is uh which uses the
broader bias and inference right says
for instance that the process of
perceptionistas is separable from
rational provided by agents process of
prolification and context top-down
effects I felt that every intermediate
level of processities has caught my
attention the way that Clark is also
talking about rationality all the way
but it's an inferential sort of
rationality
and pervasive influencer reasoning seems
to imply impervasive content
and then predictive processing seems to
be incompatible with radically inactive
rationality
well but there is uh the time there was
and I think we can still argue in
several of the there's no
non-hemorrhoids and reading of
predictive processing
which uses for instance a one first step
would be to use a deflationary sense of
prediction that understand Camaro in a
short paper from 2013 but fourth where
the values of two or more variables
cover your value reliably so the value
of 1 allows the Observer to infer the
value of another and here the inference
is happening happening at the level of
the observation not at one far
variable is inferring the value of
another so the idea would be I think
that content is in the eye of the
beholder the person who interprets how
the selection of censorial we put
approximates internal predictions he
understood in the deflationary sense can
describe it in inferential and biasing
terms so this is how I see for instance
the the idea about fourth house by Bruno
marstein in that paper which if I'm not
mistaken
title is something like the brain is not
a scientist and the argument is in this
General interaction
that we are projecting how
scientists construe brain activity as a
feature of the brain itself as if it
were predicting an inferring this more
uh robust or waiter sense
so what I'm trying to say here is that
active inference then I use double I
want to say double forgot the name of
this in English sorry
um it's not uh the literal sense of
inference here according to radically
inactive
rationalities that unarmed for the
efficiency of co-oriented behavior the
agent has to act in certain ways in
order for his his or her States come to
fruition more efficiently less costly
this does not imply the more contentious
claim that the generative models
themselves display and perform
predictive inferences this is a very
deflationary reading into predictive
processing to to provide this
combination with radical and active
rationality
and here is a kickoff in a paper from
by model it doesn't follow that an
organism has an internal
representational model of its niche in
that it is this model that those are the
cognitive work if you like instead an
organism is a model that is the causal
and statistical regularities reflect in
some environmental reflecting some
phenotype there is a model
and well
this relates to something that recently
uh
my colleague notifica and I have been
talking about the idea of how organisms
bring forth a world according to an
activism which is idea that the organism
and environment are historically
historically called determined so
uh artificial genetical scale this could
be explained through the idea of Niche
construction the idea that once an
organism is active in its environment it
promotes changes then if they are stable
enough that it can be inherited by its
Offspring and these changes provide new
evolutionary press pressure pressures
that are uh that lead its evolutionary
path a similar idea has also been
explored by other description this time
relating Niche Construction
and the ecological psychology
so my my response to that objection is
that to act rationally means to achieve
a proficient engagement with the
environment through in a way prediction
and urbanization I'm willing to accept
that characterization but
rational and broader biasian processes
need not imply content for cognition if
we
if we understand that in the Flash no
sense prediction and narrow minimization
involve the selection of input and the
coordination of an interabilities in
World involvement manners which is well
exactly the main claim of radical and
active personality so I think to that
extent that predictive processing is not
uh an enemies would be rather than a lie
of this idea instead of uh
arrival but of course there are other
issues of compatibility that I haven't I
haven't touched upon here but that uh
this is all that I have thought of but
today thank you
awesome thank you very much
all right
cool very interesting
for those who are watching live please
feel free to write any questions I will
gather my notes and let's begin the
discussion
okay
well first just uh thanks again for the
talk
how about a little context on how you
came to be asking these questions in
your current position and how your
interests in this area developed because
there's so many interesting ideas and I
just wanted to learn more about how you
came to this Framing and sharpened your
point
okay thank you that's that's a good
question because it's not often that you
can explore this background
it matters so uh I was at the time I
think I was writing my PhD dissertation
it was maybe 2007 or something
and uh I was arguing for the idea that
rationality must be something that is
ultimately World involved in there is a
tendency to think of well even among as
I told as I showed you among uh in in
embodied periods with people of certain
it needs to be essentially World
involving such as acting and practice
and so forth
and perception of course but rationality
remains something like not realizable
notion something that cannot be brought
down to the level of the the it could
not be scaled down in a way
like perception that could be explained
by a certain Dynamic engagement and so
on and so forth
so at the time I was thinking that well
maybe this is
an issue because
on other
other contexts it is taken to imply that
whatever perception moves if it is not
articulated in a way to provide a
certain fit with
professional combination then perception
is a given and this is the myth of the
given I mentioned at the beginning and I
thought that well maybe this is
something of there is something of a
myth of the given working here on an
active cognition but this is not I think
it's not fatal because we couldn't
principle argue that instead of
uh construing step perception and other
basic forms of combinations involving
Concepts and the like maybe we could
argue
from the other direction try to scale
down rationality in more not naturalized
level of
uh
the perceptual organization and the like
so that was the motivation and it was
very it was a long review process and I
believe that my first the first version
of the paper the the viewer was very I
think they were correct entirely I I
endorsed the suggestion after all but he
was very uh
they were very adamant on taking that
apart and I think it was for the better
because it it is another literature it
is another uh a lot of references that
are not usually in conversation with an
activism and body recognition and it was
very difficult just to put the matter in
the same terms to advance my arguments
so it's something that I scratched out
and I haven't thought too much about
that system but I think it's something I
would like to come back to and maybe uh
even probably someone has done so in the
in this last few years I'm not aware I
can remember but
this relation between an activism the
myth that we give and it seemed to be it
seems to be very
obvious so it is I think something that
we could we should I mean uh be able to
explore but there's not something that
was in the the Forefront of the paper
but
but I had this idea to talk about
rationality in the flashing every sense
and at the same time I was reading a lot
about uh
recording from a philosophical
perspective of course I'm not as I said
very well versed in the technicalities
and the formalities of the the approach
but I was interested in the the
philosophical consequences there and I
thought well maybe there's something to
compare here because as Clark's
quotation show you can talk about
rationality all the way and uh that's
something I wanted to to develop but not
in a cognitivist view but not radically
embodied film so that's the the the
background
awesome thank you could you maybe
describe just what is the myth of the
given what was the context that that
myth arose in and where do we go after
bringing up the myth of the given
because I I saw it as a concept that you
wove in so what was it about
okay so the middle beginning that well
there are several
Givens depending on your flavor of
philosopher's mind but most classically
in previous fields of the Mind take the
the the content of perception to be
given prayer rationally in a way that we
have certain inputs that are uh just
received by the mind and the mind
interprets it so sellers different
sellers is famous for
uh having described his uh this problem
as a problem for not only increases
fields of the mind but also for
rationalists but on the on the other
side rational is usually taken uh
rational intuition as a given which is
to say that there is some some level of
cognition that is uh unarticulated it's
given or as some people talk about being
bred given
but in a way there is this level of
cognition that is given in the mind has
to interpret it but if it is given in
this way it has no point of contact no
uh intersection between whatever
whatever mind does and the in this basic
level of uh domination so my idea is to
avoid the the charge of being committed
to the myth of the given but again this
is not something that is explicit in the
the next literature but it's something
that seems to be possible to to develop
in a
I mean uh in this sort of comparison but
it's not
it's not from the
not clearly there but
one way of solving them for the given is
to say that perceptual content is
already conceptual in nature which is
for instance how Joe McDowell does in
mind the more of that in a way
perception uh the the joke is comes with
subtitles you interpret the world as as
you do but uh
I think that one way or another way is
to demystify you know a rationality and
the upper layers of combination try and
try to think of them uh in less
uh content for analysis
without committing them so it's strictly
speaking with a level of content that is
divorced from basic levels of domination
that's one way I think of doing so and
rationality seems to be the one key
concept to do this because
it's so usually soon to be something
exclusively human and something that is
related to reasoning
and well if it is so then rationality
cannot inform action and if of course if
action is contentless in nature so if
rationality is a sense essentially
contentful and it actually is
essentially uncontent for contentless
then you can you do not have this
uh that's done this uh intersection
between two domains and this is
something I wanted to avoid but as I
told you it became so hard to express
this views in in
sufficiently clear and general way is
that by recommendation of a reviewer I
scratched it out and I
I still think about it but not in I
haven't developed a proper
line of argumentation that deals with it
more clearly than I can do as I just did
in very general terms
cool well some words that you associated
with rationality were adaptivity
and also proficiency so what do you see
as the relationship of rationality and
Fitness
as a biological function right yes yeah
okay I um
I think it is it is an intrinsic
Revelation really I think it is uh
probably the most uh
the
um obvious consequence of rational
action at a special scale
and when we talk about whether
rationality is a feature of uh certain
species or instead of uh individuals I
think Fitness is one of the
the key concept here to to think this as
the the outcome of this
rational action
so although I do not say I do not put
eating those matters in the paper I
think it is possible to think it that
way and don't see it as a
uh as an objection to think think of
rationality but again it's very liberal
and I'm willing to to accept this
consequence that well every living
organism in a way if it if it hasn't
gone Instinct yet so it is in a way
fitted to its environment so I'm willing
to say that it may involve a minimal
level of rationality of dealing with uh
the negatively changing environment
but well
it's the price of having a very
uh for labor or Progressive notion of
rationalities this is a consequence of
it I believe
so you've said that Fitness is is a
consequence of rational Behavior
are there other consequences or how do
we recognize rationality from the
outside other than just saying well the
ant colony is thriving so to the extent
that it is rational it is adaptive an
exhibiting agency and all of that
um is this such a deflationary
rationality concept that all extant
things humans and otherwise are merely
described by it or are there some
outcomes that we can use to disentangle
like for example a rational or
irrational behavior from merely the
consequences reflected by survival and
Fitness
right well I I had to to think very
carefully about this because I don't
want to trivialize this concept in a way
that well everything is IPS of fact or
rational by the matter of fact that it's
living it is acting relationship but I
think that uh in particular cases one
could uh identify the nation that I am
equal to the individuals
um self-sustainment in that Niche so so
at the individual level in particular
okay this is one conclusion you see
certain actions that could classifiers
irrational to the extent that they uh
are detrimental to to with survival but
uh at the species level it's more
difficult to argue that way because to
identify this kind of behavior or
consequence but I think that in order
to not to trivialize the idea of
rationality and say well everything that
is living is it's a factorized you'd
have to to identify this sort of
particular acts that are detrimented to
to one survival
so in the case of the the ant colony I
don't know maybe
welcoming invasers would be a
would be the sort of behavior that would
be prejudicial with
survival as such
I don't know I don't know if this is uh
it's one impossible way of thinking
about this I had to think more clearly
but
cool very interesting and you brought in
in that answer and in the presentation
like multiple
nested time scales just like Eco Evo
Devo does from a more biological
perspective looking at how Niche
construction Bridges the gap between
slower phylogenetic processes and more
rapid developmental processes
um so how does this
embedded and multi-scale consideration
relate to the the content
concept like is content going to be
localized in one body or is the content
distributed across entities or is the
rationality distributed across entities
how would we even identify the locus
of rationality and that also kind of
invokes the um horizontal and modular
conception from the quote that you
provided so how do we identify a salient
spatial temporal scales and systems of
Interest
oh I I don't know I don't know if I can
answer uh this fully but
it seems to me that at the level of uh
if we're talking about content for
instance content as a accuracy
conditions for symbolic thoughts I think
fortunately we have to say that it's
it's not localized in a single
individual it's publicly shared so you
can say that
um
one consequence of this is that it's
possible to think of different uh
patterns of reasoning that have
being information
sites at different times Etc and you can
see that well they developed different
level different uh rules for Content
information
and I think this is
plausible to say that content is
is localized that the the
uh how can you say it's share the amount
you know the specifics of
just for rationality I think
one could
[Music]
identify in particular behaviors
if it if it feeds these uh
this kind of description of uh spin
professional proficient interaction and
adaptive interaction between an organism
and its environment its Niche so
probably we could
we could give different answers here a
rationality and content I I am willing
to say that
content for organization is not
something that happens in the head
something that is out there in a way
shared among others and this is
something that the philosophy of mine
has at least since the 60s uh the
philosophers of mine have been argued
for the idea that content is externally
individuated
and uh I'm I think this is it is one of
the video by for instance Hillary Putnam
and Tyler Burge and others that
mental content is individuated at the
community level or societal level but
along the on the other hand they think
rationality could be in principle
individuated in particular behaviors but
it would depend on the individuals goals
and the the niche it inhabits and so on
so forth
uh there are of course the actual
variables here that might be important
too
to identify
Behavior as rational or not
thanks um well one phrase that really
stuck with me was like know how not know
that
perhaps uh a basal point in your work
and a focus on that action so I just
wanted to
hear about how action and practice as
you wove them here today how are those
terms addressed
and how are things different today with
the treatment of action and practice and
know-how not know that than say in the
helmholtzee in days or even in ancient
or in World Knowledge traditions
So Okay cool so the idea I think would
be that
um
there is a tendency from uh it is a
tendency from a very modern philosophy
but it has been very influential in that
the first wave of cognitive science to
think of perception as a capacity to
categorize the environment and to offer
a discrete description of environmental
aspects so for instance perceiving that
uh the the the the
I don't know the the curve is to my left
is a matter of knowing that there is a
thing with searches such properties to
my left and this is a kind of uh know
that a kind of propositional attitude
towards the world so
uh I think the the
interesting thing about an activism and
ecological psychology as well and to the
extent that they recall American
pragmatism from the the beginning of the
centuries to think of
perception as a matter of not
categorizing these properties in the
world but as uh disclosing possibilities
for acting
and this is something that if you were
to explain that in terms of uh in
epistemic terms such as knowledge we
wouldn't put it as a matter of knowing
that the the curve is to my left but
knowing how to grab the cup and and do
whatever I want to do with it if I want
to drink a cup of coffee or if I want to
use it as a paperweight it will have
different silent properties and this is
something that
although it has been I think
very I think an activism and ecological
psychology and other embodied views of
cognition have been largely successfully
in shifting this discussion to this
point I think in the uh in more
traditional cognitive Sciences you still
have the idea that well organism
organisms perceived by by describing the
way the environment the the things this
is something that I think
uh more traditional readings of
predictive processing make uh make clear
as in uh the idea that you're inferring
about the the source of stimuli and not
in uh and not and this is not I mean
this is more easily amenable to the idea
that the brain or the cognitive system
knows that
the the world is so and so
the environment is so and so instead of
saying that the cognitive system knows
how to engage with the world and I
believe the
the the the point that
an activists and uh ecological
psychologists are trying to make is to
and also working on the the predictive
coding and the free energy principle
Etc is to show that these Notions these
Frameworks could be a minimal idea that
the cognitive system is knowing how to
engage it knows how to engage the
environment in a way it doesn't need to
be read in a handboard summary
that the the Kindle system is inferring
that the world is so so I think this is
one way of explaining but also uh
philosophically if you have a large at
the beginning of the the last few
decades uh a gigantic discussion about
whether you know how could be reduced to
know that and then again you have a
background of this and other
philosophical discussion about the
rather know how could be treated as an
independent notion from you know that
and whether you could
reduce one to the other and so forth so
I think it doesn't stop there you cannot
uh even though I can make a a claim for
perceptional some other knowing how
they're still the the background issue
of whether know-how could be treated as
and all that
and this is something that I am also
working on recently
there's a lot to say there it's it's
such an interesting idea especially with
linguistic communication it's a little
bit like the finger and the moon and
talking about the moon but the finger is
only where it is and we're not talking
about the pointer we're talking about
the reference
and so to use
a sociocognitive form of communication
in in cultured language
or in written academic discourse to peer
through that or to reimagine that and
see even what seems to be like the
Pinnacle of know that
and still see it as know how
I guess the question there is
how do we read papers
yes of course yes I think it is uh it is
a
uh it's yeah the values it seems to have
to be a very big problem because if we
try to to treat these negative
capacities as you mentioned as a matter
of know-how
it seems that we still miss something
about communication for instance and on
the other hand I think and this is my
Innovation but I think that we could in
principle talk about
how
understanding what you just said and
trying to respond to it is a matter of
knowing how to behave linguistically
but I think that even this movement
to treat high levels of
combinationalists which made it a matter
of know-how it still leaves something
out I am at I mean personally I am
and pleased with it I think at some
level we've got to say that well that is
another kind of approach that is needed
here to explain how we communicate for
instance in
periodically not to say that it does not
involve and now but it's not just that I
think that at least more than practical
knowledge is needed
but maybe the key here is to think of
practical knowledge just basic and
necessary for other sorts of other other
kinds of knowledge that they are needed
to engage in this sort of Exchange
maybe maybe the maybe this is one layer
I'm sure that
well
uh more has to be
said about this to give them a more
informative answer but this is a at
least my current position is that
no how provides the basis of our
engagement with the world and with
others but that some juncture we have to
to be able to develop other kinds of
understanding to explain a terrorists to
explain the complex sorts of uh
exchanges we have in our daily lives
such as reading papers as you said
I I agree I think
framing know that as the basis and then
recovering know how is a challenge and
it's also a challenge to begin with the
basal cognitive processes as being
enacted no house and to reassemble those
know-how pieces into know that again
it's not necessarily even a simple
challenge but would we rather confront
the challenge of assembling symbolic
propositional declarative verbal
Etc cognitive processes from a more
liminal
ecological cognitive approach
or try to recover the ecological from
the turing machine in a sense so it
seems like
um
you're speaking in support of grounding
in ecological plausible basal cognitive
processes and then working towards
assembling the skyscraper
yes yes yeah totally yeah I think it's
well
both are uh those both approaches are
difficult to to
to assemble as you said to to to provide
this uh sort of explanation either
bottom left or top down but I am more
favorable of course to the the one web
approach I think it also for another
reason it it seems to the point of
departure seems to be uh on biological
description of how we interact with the
world and the other way around it seems
to be much more difficult to explain uh
how we come up with this uh biological
questions such as our body morphology
and such it seems that we have to first
account for that and then we we get to
the the other questions which are also
hard to to answer but at the very least
I I think it's a
the bottom up approach is more
integrative you know is that the chances
are it seems to be more
uh in our favor in the sense
and and the way you just kind of framed
it made me think that if you were to
program a computer from scratch
it could be an abstract or a virtual
computer so it doesn't even need to have
a specific embodiment
and in that situation one might be
concerned with assembling
know that assert that and assembling
these declarative
statements and logic processes into
something that is more dynamical or in
interacting with the environment however
that process of like full stack
engineering
with logic and silicone at the base
is quite different from how we got here
and so it might but it's it's
complimentary
um well you gave a little visibility
into uh I guess the before during and
after of peer review so I was just
curious what
changed during and after the paper like
over the last months or years or however
long it was how did you evolve on this
and then what do you see as relevant
next steps whether they're for you or
just general to be done are we looking
for a brain measurement are we looking
for a video camera in a forest are we
looking for a conceptual Advance what is
going to move forward past your
developments
that's that's a great question I think
um
I I'm not completely satisfied with the
way I always find the people at the
conceptual level I don't know if this
any of these would be carried out in uh
I honestly don't know if you could in
principle carried out in other empirical
terms but
uh I'm not saying that uh well one is I
would write it a bit differently today
not that it's uh not that I disagree
with the paper originally but I think I
there's something some points that I
would like to reframe but they do not
authorize I think he had a new paper
but maybe in the future but this is
something that
uh the questions such as the myths of
the evening which is still the
philosophical question
and conceptual one they still uh bother
me but I have yet to
to find opportunity to develop these
ideas more carefully and the the general
view I put forth there I think I I think
it still stands
uh but
um
I would like I I still
I'm waiting for this chance to elaborate
it further and see how far I can get but
I don't know yet I must admit I don't
know what are the the future
developments of this idea but um I've
been working on several isolated
issues on this approach
for the last few years I've worked with
the notion of information and scientific
understanding and information for
ecological and and activists of
combination and recently I am working
more recently with a few colleges on
virtual reality and perception
recognition so uh
this is how I like to to conduct my
research to find interesting
uh questions and see how how can I deal
with them but not necessarily find
myself
uh tied to one
one line of reasoning by the way so this
is what happened at the time I was
working with rationality if I thought it
was a very cool subject and uh I still
think it is but I haven't had the time
to come back and reframe what I wanted
to but uh maybe maybe sometime in the
near future I don't know but more the
most recent thing I've been working on
does not involved in cellular
rationality but I think some products
could be wrong which is that of uh
virtual reality and how does uh visual
reality actually compares to combination
because
well there's obviously something missing
from a perseverance in a visual
environment right
um there is of course if I someone for
instance if if I'm on a visual
environment where I am under a kind of
threat I may feel something analogous to
fear but I'm not really fearing for my
life
and imagine this that the person on the
virtual reality so is it rational to to
run away from
the the that threat the visual threat
and so on so forth this is this the the
this is what I'm working on and uh maybe
it's it provides a point of return to
this
the idea of radical and active
rationality and in fact uh the paper
just got accepted so as I was telling
you before I was so busy these last few
days because we were correcting proofs
my colleagues and I never figured
uh and I I was
with a tight schedule too
to submit the corrected version of the
paper in the last few weeks and then I
got the proofs and
well maybe uh in the future I can come
back to the issue of rationality I'd
like to but I don't know if I I don't
know I I really can't foresee the
developments of that but uh in general I
still agree with my original idea but
I'll frame it differently a little bit
so the VR point I'm sure that there's a
lot more to say there but it reminded me
of just the title virtual reality it's a
virtualization and so in the same way
that
cognitive action planning
allows us to entertain
policies that our body doesn't take
if only to evaluate them and choose
against them but we can go on a flight
of fancy have a Whimsical policy
selection process
of counterfactuals
mentally
but then our morphology is kind of like
our Lifeline you know if you actually
fall off a ledge then it's going to hurt
and then in virtual reality
you're embodied
perceptual experience is quite literally
a virtualization of
survival critical situations so you
might see yourself as being on a ledge
but you're on a flat floor
and then in that situation
if you're kind of
um a cognitive Observer outside of the
video game you might say well it's
rational for me just to fall off to see
what happens
so that's like but then there's a layer
of rationality within the space yes like
what's a good move in the game
um and so it's kind of blurring the line
between
[Music]
it's it's blurring the criticality of
the body and um
well
I'm sure you've thought about this much
more so how does this play into our
virtual reality
um with the ways we think about and use
and design these systems
well this is the the the the the the
questions that motivated us to write a
paper and uh not uh give them and I was
that in the technical literature you see
that a lot of researchers working with
the uh treat uh visual perception as
illusory a kind of Illusion but we were
a bit bothered by that because on the
other hand it only works in VR because
we we embodied the devices devices they
work for us you have the controllers you
have the the headset and uh it seems so
weird to say that the user the the user
is under a kind of Illusion
and on the other hand it seems that it's
not actually cognition because as you
said there is no there is no biological
relevance to those uh cognitive States
so to speak for instance if I see an
apple in VR it's it does not afford
nourishing but it makes sense within the
game right but the different uh well
what I perceive an apple in a in an
actual environment it is it affords
nourishment it is something I can eat
but not in VR I can pretend to
so we coined this concept of allusion to
explain
it is as if we were
facing an actual animal but it involves
also this volition of play this idea
that we are not
being sled because we put on the
equipment we know we are in the game and
this I think is a hot subject right now
because there's metaphors method and I
am very skeptical of whatever that can
people are very optimistic but about the
possibilities of the metaverse and some
others really think that we could be in
a simulation institutely speaking but I
mean the best technology the current
technology shows us is that it's very
limited and you can pretend to be in a
certain environment and so forth and
this I think may offer a new new ways of
thinking of
thinking about rationality in this
visual environment in ways that maybe
Russians do something that environment
has said to jump off the television see
what happens and on the other hand
behavioral aspects of doing so sometimes
people actually feel fear and people
face the street for phobias with virtual
realities
and
um it's it's a lot of there's a lot of
interesting questions there that
maybe I mean for future research we can
yeah back to it it made me think about
how the Apple in real life it could be
calories for you but also it could be
calories for a fly it could be thrown
you could use it as a hammer you could
paint it right so
ecology
and the generative process as we'd say
an active inference kind of
is always going Beyond
whatever affordances were programmed in
for a given object and then also
um the current discourse on VR focuses
heavily on headsets
just speaking totally anecdotally not
not my expert area
um it seems a little bit interesting
it's like as if the mobile phone
discussion was only focused on
rectangles of a certain size
what makes this not virtual reality it's
like looking through a window and
there's another fellow to speak with so
it's not attached to my head it doesn't
have some of the motion tracking
um capacities that some technologies
have but it is
a niche modification in Perry personal
space
and we can push
signals and affordances to each other
so having a VR framing or really just a
framing of rationality and perception
cognition action Cycles
that
aren't just constrained to one specific
realization or Hardware type and could
run the gamut from Total offline
person in a field
to somebody who's very
in The Matrix
seems pretty relevant otherwise new
technologies even little variants and
software updates will continue to just
infinitely surprise and confuse
yeah I think it's a it's a it's hard to
define the uh
I mean we are here in an exchange which
I think it could in principle be
classified as a form of virtual reality
of course I'm seeing your own your C
mind but
uh I mean most I think works out they
nowadays they they find it a doc by
saying that well must have a headset and
sometimes a controller but but other
than that it's not spiritual reality but
yeah it's hard to Define anything uh
it's not it's not a dump and
straightforward as one will think
because on uh talking commercially of
course virtual reality means headsets
and and other paraphernalia but a phone
just talking on the phone or a telegraph
in that time
it would have been on that interface
with that sensory modality and with
those affordances it is the
virtualization
yeah that we have access to of just a
different chapter today
yeah I think so yes part of our paper
was to argue that in a way embodying
technological devices is obviously in
the need not that's not new it is the
mark of Being Human
it's embodying technological devices
what made us what we are since the
beginning using analytic technology
and the fact that we can embody it so
proficiently a device even if it is
programmed to for instance uh in within
virtual reality to have something a
creature you control us richer with new
morphology another morphology for
instance even if that's the case it only
happens so proficiently because we are
able to embody the device some
experiments have shown that you can map
for instance a Twist of your wrist to a
third arm
uh that individual reality goes from was
that from your chest and people can
learn to control this third arm that
doesn't map into our actual morphology
but it can be made so by a Twist of the
wrist so
this is something we will discussed in
our paper that well you can
you can only do that because you embody
the device so you can see it's an
illusion
it's actually well
part of what means being human is to
embody technological devices so
I would go that way I mean I know it
blurs the distinction between virtual
and non-virtual but I think that's one
way of dealing with this
cool is there anything else you want to
talk about ask or just kind of Prelude
ah well I I'd like to thank you for the
opportunity to discuss this paper it was
very nice for me I I really enjoyed it
and this is uh very nice and uh
comfortable environment to discuss these
issues and think I think once again
thank you yeah awesome discussion and
important topics and we'll be happy to
talk to you again anytime
okay thank you farewell thank you